<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ninth of September. 1622. Count Mansfields proceedings since the last battaile with the great misfortune which hath lately hapned to the Duke of Brunswicke VVith the great victory obtained by the Protestants in France, by those of the Towne of Mompeliers against the Kings forces, who fought to take the towne by treachery, but were most of them put to the sword. Also relating another skirmish, which happened betweene Count Mansfield and Don Cordua in the prouince of Henego, with the great sea fight betweene some of the Hollanders bound for the West Indies meeting with the Spaniards. Likewise a new and great slaughter made vpon Spinola his forces hefore [sic] Bergen vp Zome, by those of the towne: with the comming downe of Bethlem Gabors brother, and the Marquis of Iagersdorp into Silesia, to inuade the country. Lastly, the taking in of the citty of Spiers by the Bauarians, with their blocking vp of Heidelburgh, Frankendale, and Mainhem, in the Palatinate. ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14992</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.76</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100652</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836483</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836483</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176342</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14992)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176342)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1317:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ninth of September. 1622. Count Mansfields proceedings since the last battaile with the great misfortune which hath lately hapned to the Duke of Brunswicke VVith the great victory obtained by the Protestants in France, by those of the Towne of Mompeliers against the Kings forces, who fought to take the towne by treachery, but were most of them put to the sword. Also relating another skirmish, which happened betweene Count Mansfield and Don Cordua in the prouince of Henego, with the great sea fight betweene some of the Hollanders bound for the West Indies meeting with the Spaniards. Likewise a new and great slaughter made vpon Spinola his forces hefore [sic] Bergen vp Zome, by those of the towne: with the comming downe of Bethlem Gabors brother, and the Marquis of Iagersdorp into Silesia, to inuade the country. Lastly, the taking in of the citty of Spiers by the Bauarians, with their blocking vp of Heidelburgh, Frankendale, and Mainhem, in the Palatinate. ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 19 [i.e. 21], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. A[llde] for Nicholas Bourne and Thomas Archer, and are to bee solde at their shops, at the Royall Exchange and Popes head Pallace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Page nos. 13-14 repeated in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 17261 on UMI microfilm reel 1317.</note>
                  <note>Some pages cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mansfeld, Peter Ernst, --  Graf von, 1580-1626 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176342:1"/>
            <p>The Ninth of September. 1622.</p>
            <p>COVNT MANSFIELDS PROCEEDINGS SINCE THE LAST BATTAILE, WITH THE Great Misfortune which hath lately hapned to the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the Great Victory obtained by the Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> by thoſe of the Towne of <hi>Mompeliers</hi> againſt the Kings Forces, who ſought to take the Towne by Trechery, but were moſt of them put to the Sword.</p>
            <p>Alſo Relating another Skirmiſh, which happened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> and <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Cordua</hi> in the Prouince of <hi>Henego,</hi> with the great Sea Fight betweene ſome of the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> bound for the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> meeting with the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Likewiſe a new and Great Slaughter made vpon</hi> Spinola <hi>his</hi> Forces before <hi>Bergen vp Zome,</hi> by thoſe of the Towne: with the comming Downe of <hi>Bethlem Gabors</hi> Brother, and the Marquis of <hi>Iagerſdorp</hi> into <hi>Sileſia,</hi> to Inuade the Country.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Taking in of the Citty of <hi>Spiers</hi> by the <hi>Baua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> with their Blocking vp of <hi>Heidelburgh, Frankendale,</hi> and <hi>Mainhem,</hi> in the <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Likewiſe the laſt Proceedings in the moſt Parts of Chriſtendome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>E. A.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne</hi> and <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to bee ſolde at their Shops, at the <hi>Royall Exchange</hi> and <hi>Popes head</hi> Pallace. 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:176342:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176342:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Spaine the <hi>6.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE French Ambaſſador is returned from <hi>Madrill</hi> into <hi>France</hi> backe againe, but the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> will not deſiſt from thoſe Articles which about a Twelue month hee agreed vpon with the Inhabitants of <hi>Velto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina.</hi> The ſaid King hath made the <hi>Venetian</hi> Generall, Generall of all the Horſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned <hi>Don Diego Piementelli,</hi> with the title and Dignity of a Marquis, quitting him 12000. Crownes which he did owe to the Exchequer, &amp; moreouer charge that 25000. Crownes ſhould be payed vnto him in ready money. He hath likewiſe giuen Order that the Gallyes which are in <hi>Sicilia,</hi> ſhall goe to reſcue <hi>Mamorra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>Naples</hi> were arriued 4. Gallyes with Souldiers, (which are to goe to <hi>Millain</hi>) &amp; 15. Cheſts with Siluer to be coyned there.</p>
               <p>The great Maſter or Commander of <hi>Malta,</hi> hath conſented at the intreaty of the Viceroy of <hi>Sicilia,</hi> that his Gallyes ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company thoſe of the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Venice the <hi>5.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>All Commotions being ceaſed in Turky, the Great <hi>Signeur</hi> went the 7. of Iuly for the firſt time after his reeſtabliſhment to the Church at <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſtatinople,</hi> and was accompanied by diuers great Officers, Commanders, and Souldiers.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Polonian</hi> Ambaſſador is lookt for euery day at his Court, being already arriued vpon the Frontiers of Turky.</p>
               <p>The Tartarians hauing made an inrode in <hi>Polonia,</hi> the Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks doe the like in the Turkiſh Dominions, and are aſſiſted by diuers Baſhawes fled vnto them ſince the Murther of <hi>Oſman</hi> the late Great <hi>Signeur.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:176342:3"/>
               <p>Here commeth newes that the Hollanders haue met 20. Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Ships neare the Riuer that flowes by St. <hi>Lucas,</hi> and ſetting vpon them they ſunke 6. the reſt was taken, ſauing ſome few that made an eſcape.</p>
               <p>The 3. Companies which did lye at the other ſide of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Goo,</hi> are to Conduct the Count of <hi>Monteri</hi> to <hi>Barcelona,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Shipped in the Gallyes of <hi>Doria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Colonell <hi>Baldirou</hi> perceiuing that the <hi>Granbunters</hi> would beſiege the Fort of St. <hi>Maria,</hi> retired himſelfe to <hi>Cleue,</hi> taking with him, his beſt moueables and a Company of Foot, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Cittizens oppoſed themſelues againſt him, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed 4. of them to be hanged.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Odenburgh the <hi>3.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>The Empreſſe being Crowned Queene of <hi>Hungary,</hi> they haue gone on in the Dyet or Parliament with the remainder points and Articles to make an end of the ſame: and firſt of all concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the receiuing of <hi>Germane</hi> Garriſons into the Frontiers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Knights and Burgeſſes would giue no way to the ſame, notwithſtanding the great perſwaſions of the Nobility &amp; Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, which vſed all meanes and deuiſes to effect the ſame. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe the Emperour deſirous to haue an end of this point, cauſed them to meet againe, and handled ſo the matter, that the Knights and Burgeſſes, being ouermatched by the Nobility and Clergie, gaue likewiſe their conſent vnto the ſame. But <hi>Bethlem Gabors</hi> Agent proteſted againſt the ſame, and the Committees of <hi>Caſhaw</hi> went home much diſcontented.</p>
               <p>Touching Religion, no alteration ſhall bee made before the next Hungarian Parliament, where ſhall be reſolued likewiſe who ſhall be Iudge when the one party ſhall complaine to bee wronged of the other: The Catholikes will not leaue the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion to the Palatine, nor the Proteſtants to the Emperour.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Vienna</hi> is great prepration made againſt the arriuall of his Maieſty and the Empreſſe.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:176342:3"/>
               <p>Heere is newes that the Brother of <hi>Bethlem Gabor,</hi> and the Count of <hi>Thurne,</hi> are marching towards <hi>Sileſia</hi> with 30000. men to inuade it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Vienna the <hi>3.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>To day arriued heere a Poſt comming from <hi>Odenburg,</hi> (being ſent to the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and the now ruling Duke of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi>) reporting that the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Dyete was happely ended, notwithſtanding the great difficulty made by the <hi>Hungarians</hi> touching the receiuing of <hi>Germane</hi> Commanders, and Souldiers into their Forts and Strong holdes, in ſuch manner that they drew their Swordes in the Parliament one againſt another, though in the abſence of the Emperour.</p>
               <p>But that neuertheleſſe the matter was ended by moſt Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and agreed in this manner; That the Fortes and Strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdes ſhould bee beſet with <hi>Germane</hi> Captaines and Enſignes, but <hi>Hungarian</hi> Lieutenants, the Souldiers being halfe of the one Nation and halfe of the other. Whereupon ſeeing that all is Concluded according to his Maieſties deſire and expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wee hope to ſee both Maieſties heere, within the ſpace of 5. dayes at the furtheſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Vienna the <hi>5.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>At this inſtant wee receiue Newes, that the <hi>Hungarians</hi> haue condiſcended to the taking in of <hi>Germane</hi> Garriſons, and diuers other points, hauing the Palatine of <hi>Hungary</hi> taken great paines to the ſame effect. And the Lord <hi>Eſterhaſi</hi> is made a Generall in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Vienna the <hi>10.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Hungarian</hi> Parliament is finiſhed, wee ſhall ſoone haue at large the Articles, and points agreed vpon, and it is certain that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176342:4"/>they haue promiſed to admit <hi>Germane</hi> Garriſon, and principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when the Enemy is at hand: as likewiſe that the Crowne ſhall be kept at <hi>Presburgh</hi> aſwell by Germans as Hungarians, being of the one Nation as many as of the other. And there are diuers Hungarian Lords gone thither of late, ſeeing diuers thinges are yet not fully finiſhed. The Emperour is likewiſe departed, and arriued at <hi>Newſtadt,</hi> to Morrow wee looke for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming heere, from whence hee ſhall take his Iourney to meete at the <hi>Regenſbergh</hi> vpon the Electorall dayes, where they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to meete, except the Biſhop of <hi>Triere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Prague the <hi>6.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>Yeſterday the Duke of <hi>Lichtenſtain</hi> (as Deputy or Viceroy of <hi>Bohemia</hi>) gaue order that all Generals, Colonels, and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, ſhould keepe their Souldiers in a readines vntill further commaund. It is thought that the Imperialiſts will ſet vpon <hi>Glatz</hi> with all their power and ſtrength; wee haue certaine newes that yet of late 150. Souldiours are gotten in <hi>Glatz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe of <hi>Klingenbergh</hi> being deſtitute of Prouand, haue been forced to ſurrender the Towne, and agreed with their Enemies that they ſhould depart with their Baggage and goods, which they did and were but 120. ſtrong. But the Imperialiſts ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing tyed the Commanders hands and feete, they did ſend him hither.</p>
               <p>The Count of <hi>Hollocke</hi> hath gotten his pardon from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. And it is thought that the Prince of <hi>Anholt</hi> will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſpeed.</p>
               <p>The Electorall day is prolonged vntill the Firſt of October next enſuing.</p>
               <p>The Trumpetter who was the 2. day of this Month, ſent by the Emperor to <hi>Glatz,</hi> comming from thence reported that the Young Count of <hi>Thurne,</hi> and all his Gentlemen about him were deckt with Hungarian apparell, to what intent he could as yet not learne.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:176342:4"/>
               <p>The 4. of this moneth wee haue ſeene here a great number of Storkes vpon the Mountaine of St. <hi>Lawrence:</hi> and the next day were many dead fiſhes, driuing with their bellies vpwards in the Riuer <hi>Moldaw.</hi> And we hold theſe things here for ſtrange and ominous.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Breſlaw the <hi>7.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Neus</hi> intending this next weeke, to march to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Glatz,</hi> did begin to muſter his forces, but hauing receiued certaine aduiſes, hee hath deferred his deſigne vntill better op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity. Thoſe of <hi>Glatz</hi> make yet dayly diuers ſallies and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions, bringing into the Towne all what they can get, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelues of all neceſſaries, keeping their Watches a league diſtant from the Towne.</p>
               <p>The Citizens at <hi>Neus</hi> are diſarmed, by commaund of the Biſhop to keepe them vnder.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Niewenburg in Saxony the <hi>10.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>We haue here certaine newes, that the Towne of <hi>Glatz</hi> holds ſtill for the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and is ſpeedily to be ſuccoured and reſcued by the Marqueſſe of <hi>Iagerenſdorp,</hi> who is at hand with diuers Turkes, Tartarians, and Hungarians, beſides the forces of the old Count of <hi>Thurn.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Lintz the <hi>13.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>Few dayes agoe were here muſtered 700. Horſe of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Colonell <hi>Herberſteyn,</hi> which are to ride to the vpper <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Franckfort the <hi>14.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>In thoſe parts the wayes are very dangerous, which hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Princes, Lords, and Imperiall Cities to leauie and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine at common charges certaine horſe and foote, to cleanſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176342:5"/>them of ſuch robbers, murthers, and vagabonds, as aſſault the Paſſengers and Trauellers.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Frankendale,</hi> that the Imperialiſts haue late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken <hi>Spiers,</hi> and hauing beſet the Towne with 2000. men, they changed the Magiſtrate, remouing the old. The Citie of <hi>Wormes</hi> feared the like alteration, as likewiſe that the goods ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued there from the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> ſhould be confiſcated.</p>
               <p>The Imperialiſts lye in the lands of the Duke of <hi>Wirtenberg,</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Thourlath,</hi> endammaging mightily the ſaid Countries.</p>
               <p>We vnderſtand that <hi>Leopoldus</hi> is to come in the <hi>Palatinate</hi> in the name of the Emperour. Likewiſe it is reported, that Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Obertront</hi> is deceaſed at <hi>Heydelbergh,</hi> his horſe are diſmiſſed.</p>
               <p>Wee are aduiſed that the Spaniſh forces are departed from the <hi>Palatinate.</hi> But the forces of the Archduke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Tilly</hi> are about <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mſheim, Praughheym, Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lebach,</hi> and other neere vnto the ſame. Thurſday laſt they tooke <hi>Spiers,</hi> to day they ſet vpon <hi>Garmerſheym. Heydelbergh, Frankendale,</hi> and <hi>Manheim,</hi> are ſtrongly beſet. Laſt Thurſday was the Hoſpitall at <hi>Worms</hi> ſet on fire by the Crabatz, which are of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours ſide.</p>
               <p>The Colonell <hi>Kniphawſen</hi> hauing left this Citie not paſt two dayes, there was ſent one from the Emperour to charge him further: but vnderſtanding his departure, he returned preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly backe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Spiers the <hi>16.</hi> of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>The 9. of this Moneth is the Bauarian Army marcht vp from <hi>Lymen,</hi> with fiue peeces of Ordnance, euery one being drawne by twelue horſe, and croſſing the Riuer at <hi>Lulſheym,</hi> they ſate downe in our Territorie, the next day came Monſieur <hi>Tilly</hi> in this Citie, but he returned the ſame day in his quarter. The ſame day in the morning arriued there likewiſe the Biſhop of this Citie, and the Archduke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> came there in the after noone about two of the clocke.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:176342:5"/>
               <p>The eleuenth of this moneth, the ſaid Armie went to beſiege <hi>Germiſhem</hi> which they got at laſt, the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth by Aſſault, having before received great dammage by the Ordinance and ſhott of the Towne, they ſlew all what they mette; and at laſt granted quarter to the reſt.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Franckfort</hi> the eighteenth of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> It is certaine that in the Lands of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> there are gathered great forces, and are to meete at <hi>Halber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadt,</hi> to what purpoſe is not divulged.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Wirtenbergh,</hi> the Marquis of <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clach</hi> and diuers other Princes are leavying ſouldiers likewiſe; having divers Commanders of the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> the Counts of <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Halberſtadt</hi> in their countryes. The Biſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> is at this preſent at <hi>Speſſert,</hi> to recreate himſelfe with hunting.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Hanaw</hi> the eighteenth of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> forces hauing left the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> to follow the Count of <hi>Mansfield; Leopoldus</hi> came preſently, thether from <hi>Alſatia,</hi> bringing divers Crabatz with him: who lye now almoſt all at <hi>Spiers,</hi> the tenth of this Moneth he went to beſiege <hi>Germerſheym</hi> being aſſiſted by the <hi>Bavarians,</hi> and got the ſame the fourth day. His Garriſon left within <hi>Spiers</hi> committed daily great outrages. The Cittizens ſtand in feare to be pillaged, as hath happened to theſe of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Lambert,</hi> and other places more. What the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have ſpared, theſe are likely to deſtroy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, having alreadie fired certaine Villages.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Heidelbergh</hi> the 15. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Armie, ſince it came before this Citie, hath
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176342:6"/>continually taken great paines to blocke, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blocke the ſame. And now very lately they haue likewiſe taken a courſe to blocke vp <hi>Mainheim</hi> and <hi>Franckendale,</hi> for they have Wormes and all the Townes hereabouts, ſo that no proviſion can come to any of theſe Townes, by which we doe verily i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine that they do meane to ſtarve theſe Townes, and ſo take them without beſieging them at all.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Collen</hi> the eighteenth of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Thoſe that haue beſieged the Fort <hi>Papenmutz,</hi> eſpying that they doe no good with their Ordinance, ſhooting from the ſide of <hi>Berghs</hi> land, then to ſpend their Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets and Gun-powder, ſpare now the ſame, vntill their Sconſe will be readie at this ſide, which will be to morrow. Of late a Citizen of this Towne, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing himſelfe vpon the Batterie called, looke in the Cap, or kyke in the mutz, was ſhott by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Fort and brought hether dead.</p>
               <p>But few daies agoe, there was a Souldier ſent with letters out of the Fort <hi>Papenmutz,</hi> but being taken by the Enemies which are neere the Fort, he was hanged before day-light at a tree to afray the other. We live here dayly in great griefe and miſery, many die ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly amongſt vs, before we can perceiue that they are ſicke, other are infected with the plague, which invades and aſſaults vs mightily: Some are growne madde, being bitten by the dogges, that had eaten the dead carkaſſes landed there at the ſhore, as we wrote the laſt time at large.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Middlebourgh</hi> the twentieth of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> At <hi>Oſtend</hi> being two men of Warre, readie to ſet forth at Sea, our men that lay with their Ships before the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176342:6"/>Towne attended vpon them, and Captaine <hi>Kleuter</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> gave charge to Captaine <hi>Iacob Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kertſon Vinck,</hi> to wayte vpon them with his Pinnace in the night time about the <hi>Geule,</hi> to diſcouer their comming forth, and as ſoone as they advanced to the Sea, he gave warning to the reſt with fyring, and other ſignes. Whereupon our men cutting preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly off their ropes, ſayled on, and mette them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Oſtende</hi> and <hi>Blankenbergh,</hi> and charged them with their Ordinance; But the enemies perceiuing that they could not come from the wall, did their beſt endeauour to returne backe againe to <hi>Oſtende,</hi> but our men followed them ſo cloſe that they were inforced to caſt themſelues on the ſhore neere the Shelfe about the <hi>Guele,</hi> where men of the States ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their Ships in the forme of a halfe a Moone, made them quite vnſeruiceable by their Ordinance, ſhooting againſt, from three a clocke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, vntill three of the clocke in the afternoone. The Citie did ſend divers boates with men to them, becauſe the Ships ſhould not be taken, and did likewiſe play with their Ordinance vpon our Ships. But the foreſaid two Ships and the boates have beene in ſuch manner dealt withall, that 164. of them are ſlaine, 90. hurt: On our ſide we have loſt ſoure men, having ſome few hurt.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding the Gallies of <hi>Malta,</hi> and of the French King are arrived at <hi>Rochell,</hi> they never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe make many excurſions both by water and by land, and have taken lately, divers Ships loaden with corne: And having taken by land, the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger or poſte of <hi>Bordeaux</hi> accompanied with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176342:7"/>twentie perſons, they offer to pay 10000. Crownes, for their ranſome. The Kings Armies are yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Rochell, Mompelliers,</hi> and <hi>Montaulban.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From <hi>Berghen</hi> vp <hi>Zoom,</hi> we vnderſtand that the enemies on a ſuddaine haue ſurpriſed three halfe Moones, but our men beate them preſently out of them, the enemie loſt in this ſervice 600. men, and States 100. They aſſault the out-workes moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Boſh gate, where they come many times ſo neere one another, that they are within the reach of a Pike.</p>
               <p>Laſt Satterday arrived there two Companies about foure of the Clocke in the afternoone, and were that ſame evening yet imployed in a hott ſervice, and the one being <hi>Switzers,</hi> mowed at that time brauely with their two handed Swords, amongſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. In this Skirmiſh were fiue hundred men ſlaine of the enemies, and fifteene onely of ours. The dead are not yet buryed, neither of this, nor the laſt Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, it is true, that there was made a ceſſation of Armes for an houre to the ſame purpoſe, but the Cittie eſpying that the Spaniards came towardes their trenches in great troupes, ſhott amongſt them, ſo that thoſe that were not ſlaine, were glad to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre to their owne Campe.</p>
               <p>There are of late landed twentie Companies, ſo that the Cittie is now of all neceſſaries provided, and in no danger, by the grace of God.</p>
               <p>The enemie having rayſed two Batteries, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammage by the Ordinance, the Ships and Boates comming and going, the Cittie hath diſmounted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176342:7"/>twice or thrice his Ordinance vpon the ſame, ſo that he reſts now with the ſame.</p>
               <p>Letters from <hi>Riga</hi> in <hi>Lithuania</hi> make mention, that the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> are by the meanes of their ſeverall Ambaſſadors treating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a Peace in their Tents in the field. But they were at the beginning very likely to breake off, in regard that the Polonian Ambaſſadour, the Kingly Dignitie of the King of <hi>Sweden:</hi> And having at laſt given him his due reſpect, they haue had divers meetings, and it is very likely that there will be a Peace concluded.</p>
               <p>They write from <hi>Genua,</hi> that the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> is arrived neare their Territorie with great Forces: which cauſed them to haue an eye vpon him, and to looke to themſelues.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Bredaw</hi> are expected divers horſe, and to the ſame purpoſe are their Stables prepared and made readie: And in <hi>Berghen op Zoom,</hi> and other places thereabout, are likewiſe great ſtore of Forces to be ſent, to what effect God knowes.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Paris</hi> the 27. of Auguſt. And now for <hi>Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> and the Biſhop that is with him. It is certaine, that the Duke of <hi>Bulloyne</hi> ſent for him, and that he came to <hi>Loraine</hi> from the place where he was in foure dayes, which is one hundred myle. The Duke of <hi>Loraine</hi> could make but 8000. to reſiſt him, ſo he was forced to compound with him, to giue him Corne and money, neuertheleſſe, he burned and ſpoyled a great many of his Meſſages, ſo the Duke <hi>de Bulloynes</hi> plot was diſcovered, for he had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to deliver into <hi>Mansfeilds</hi> hands three Townes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176342:8"/>in <hi>France,</hi> whereof <hi>Saus</hi> in <hi>Burgon</hi> was one of the three, ſo he marched downe towards <hi>Sedan,</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Bulloyne.</hi> The King hearing of this, ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from his Armie Duke <hi>Denawers,</hi> Duke <hi>de Angu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lame,</hi> Duke <hi>de Lonigewen,</hi> to levell Forces for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite him with all ſpeed; and as he marched he came to a Cittie which is called <hi>Munſon,</hi> which is vpon the border of <hi>France,</hi> but not in <hi>France.</hi> And then the the Duke <hi>de Naweres</hi> and <hi>Mansfield</hi> came to a parley, ſo that the Duke brought him to the Cittie with him, and placed his Armie cloſe vnder the Walles, and was faine to furniſh his Armie with bread and victualles, ſo he told the Duke that both he and his Armie were at the Kings ſervice, in giuing him foure hundred thouſand Crownes, and a yearely penſion, and ſhewed him ſeven Letters which the Duke <hi>de Bulloyne</hi> had written to him. This the Duke writ to the King: in the meane time, the French levelled great Armies, both of foote and horſe. And the Duke entertained him, vntill the Kings anſwere came, which was done with great diſcretion, for the Kings Armies are now with the three Dukes in bringing to a head; in two dayes they are in ſeverall places thirtie fiue thouſand, and <hi>Mansfeild</hi> is twelue thouſand Foote, and eyght thouſand Horſe: he told the Duke, that there is fiue thouſand of the eyght thouſand Horſemen, the beſt in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>The Biſhoppe perceiuing that <hi>Mansfeild</hi> would make his owne peace, and leaue him, there grew a Mutinie in the Armie: and the Biſhoppe would haue left <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and haue gone to the Duke
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176342:8"/>of <hi>Bulloyne,</hi> but the Duke <hi>Denaweres,</hi> pacified them both.</p>
               <p>This I thinke was to colour their intent, ſo in the end the Kings anſwere came, which was this; He would neyther of his ſervice, nor his Armie, nor giue him any money, ſo the Duke <hi>Denaweres</hi> and he parted, and he went away without doing any harme, ſo <hi>Mansfeild</hi> went and conferred with the Duke of <hi>Bulloyne,</hi> in the fields in their Coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and each of them had three hundred men; what the Conference was we know not, neyther can we tell what <hi>Mansfeild</hi> will doe yet. But he hath burned and ſpoyled in <hi>Loraine,</hi> and vpon the borders of <hi>France,</hi> ſixtie Villages and Caſtles, and he is very rich in robbing the Churches of their Chaliſes and Croſſes, and Images, and he hath fiue thouſand Women or Whores in his Campe. The Duke <hi>de Bulloine</hi> ſo ſoone as he heard that <hi>Mansfeild</hi> was come into <hi>Loraine,</hi> levelled all the moneyes that was due to the King for this yeare, and fiue yeares to come, in all parts round about him, and forced them to make ſhift to pay him, and thoſe that would not, nor could not pay ſo ſuddenly, he hanged them, and killed and hanged fiue of the Kings owne ſervants, that were there to receiue the Kings Rents. And now of late he hath furniſhed <hi>Mansfield</hi> with Powder and other things, and hath bought all the Corne he can, and brought it into <hi>Sedan;</hi> We ſhall know within theſe ſixe dayes, what they will doe, <hi>Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild</hi> cannot goe backe againe, for the Emperours Armie lyeth in waite for him, and if he come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176342:9"/>
                  <hi>France,</hi> neither he nor any of his Armie will euer returne backe againe. The Queene is going to <hi>Molenes,</hi> where the Queene mother is at the hot bathe. Newes is here that duke <hi>de Soulte</hi> was ſtayd and put in priſon, and from thence both Queenes goe to <hi>Lyons,</hi> for there the kings meets them. Then here is none left here but Monſieur the Kings brother.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Munpilliard</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> it is reported that the Prince of <hi>Condie,</hi> comming before the ſame, ſent into the Cittie a Cardinall, with 3. other noblemen, to treat for a Peace, and in the meane time ſet vpon the Out-workes of the ſaid cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and tooke in one of the halfe Moones thereof, which the towne perceiuing, told the aforeſaid noble men of their tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, and willed them to depart the citty before the Sunne was two houres hie, all which the noble men did performe, but they were no ſooner out of the Cittie, &amp; come to their owne Forces, but the towne ſent out forces, which tooke in againe the aforeſaid halfe Moone, &amp; ſlew the Cardinal, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue 300. men of note And of the Nobilitie were ſlaine, the Duke <hi>de Benf,</hi> coſin to the King, the Duke <hi>de Fronſac,</hi> ſon to the Count of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> coſin to the King, the Duke <hi>de Enſarx,</hi> coſin to the King, the count <hi>d'Alanx,</hi> ſon to the count <hi>d'O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uergne,</hi> the Cardinal <hi>de la Valette,</hi> the ſon of the Duke <hi>d'Eſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> the Marquis <hi>d'Alu,</hi> ſon to Monſieur <hi>de Souddy,</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>de Benleron,</hi> governour <hi>de falaiſe,</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Candſy,</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor of S. <hi>Lo,</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Vandoſme,</hi> Knight, the ſonne of Monſieur <hi>d'Alincourt,</hi> gouernor <hi>de Lyons,</hi> the ſonne of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Montigny,</hi> gouernor <hi>de Diepe,</hi> the eldeſt and youngeſt ſons of the count <hi>de Schoubergne,</hi> the count <hi>de Rochefort</hi> ſon of Monſieur <hi>de Munthaſon</hi> governor of <hi>Paris,</hi> the Mariſchall <hi>de brandes,</hi> brother to Monſieur <hi>de Luines,</hi> the Mariſchall <hi>de Vitay,</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Montmoreincy,</hi> Admirall of <hi>France,</hi> hurt in two places with a Pyke, &amp;c. After this fight the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the Citie were ſafely returned back to their Campe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:176342:9"/>
               <head>From Rochel.</head>
               <p>Your newes from <hi>Rochel,</hi> touching ſinking of the Kings Gallyes, is not true: for there arriued the laſt Weeke a Barke at <hi>Barſtable</hi> from <hi>Rochel,</hi> which was not aboue eight dayes homeward; and they report, the Kings ſhippes are in the Riuer of <hi>Breſt Andbrenager,</hi> &amp; ſo vigilantly watched by 60. ſayle of <hi>Rochellers,</hi> that they cannot ioyne; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that doubtleſſe the <hi>Rochellers</hi> will be Maſters of the Sea this Winter, whereby all other the <hi>French</hi> Kings ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects will be exceedingly diſturbed in their Trade, and the <hi>Rochellers</hi> will be much encreaſed and ſtrengthened, which happily may procure peace the ſooner vnto the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants throughout the Kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>¶ The Copie of a Letter ſent from <hi>Breda,</hi> ſince the Arriuall of Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> relating the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of the late Battell, being fought on <hi>the</hi> 29. <hi>of Auguſt: With his Proceedings ſince.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter <hi>Mansfield</hi> was arriued at <hi>Iambloies, Don Cordua</hi> with moſt of the Countrey Bores, got to a Towne called <hi>Leymon,</hi> by which <hi>Mansfield</hi> muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie paſſe, and ſo was conſtrained to encounter him: The oppoſition that came againſt <hi>Mansfield</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> was for certaine betweene 30. or 40000. Bores and Souldiers together, who had ſo ſtrongly intrenched themſelues, and placed their Ordenance, before <hi>Mansfields</hi> comming, that to paſſe through them, was very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; which of neceſſitie they muſt doe, before they could get any paſſage towards <hi>Breda.</hi> It is moſt credible, that <hi>Mansfields</hi> horſemen, after they had encompaſſed <hi>Gonzales de Cordua's</hi> Forces, did ſo valiantly behaue themſelues, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176342:10"/>on a ſudden they were put to a great rout: ſo that Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> by meanes of certaine companies of his horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſurprized their Ordenance from the Bores, the which they kept couragiouſly for the ſpace of two houres, in this time they were imployed vpon the enemies, they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing not wherewith to defend themſelues: ſo that by the meanes of loſing their Ordenance, they were ſlaine in great multitudes. Yet notwithſtanding, the multitudes of Bores were ſo great, being thruſt forward by <hi>Don Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua's</hi> old ſouldiers, that they gathered a head, and obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their Ordenance once againe. But before they were wholly recouered, the enemie loſt aboue 1000. men. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing animated on both ſides, the Battell at this time conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued very fierce, wherein the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> behaued himſelfe moſt valiantly, inſomuch that hee receiued a ſhot in the left Arme, neere vnto the Wreſt; and notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this misfortune, hee would not leaue the Field, but fought ſtill couragiouſly at leaſt the ſpace of foure houres; in which time he met with <hi>Gonzales de Cordua</hi> in perſon: whereupon the Duke (it ſeemes) not reſpecting his woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Arme, couragiouſly made two ſhots at him with his Piſtoll, and it is thought one of them tooke effect, for here is newes come, that he is ſlaine. This is certaine, hee is at this time miſſing, and not to be found; but the truth of this you ſhall ſhortly heare. The Duke of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke</hi> ſtill preſt further among his enemies, proſecuting the Bores, who ſwarmed about him in great multitudes, that in the end the Duke loſt his Standard, and receiued another ſhot in the middle of his Arme, and yet would not leaue the Field for a good while after, as it ſeemes not regarding the two Wounds hee had receiued on his left Arme; which the whole Field, as well enemies as friends, admired to ſee his worthie to bee prayſed valour.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176342:10"/>A little before the Battell was ended, hee was conſtrayned to leaue the Field, in regard of the Wounds hee receiued on his Arme, the loſſe of which is and ought to bee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for by all true Proteſtants. After this, hee was conueyed out of the Armie, in a Horſe-Litter made of Reedes, to ſome ſecure place for his ſafetie; but going with great haſt, hee vnfortunately fell downe vpon the foreſaid Arme, part whereof being cut off; which did ſo inflame the Wound, that he was enforced once againe to haue it cut off a little below the elbow. As for Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> he ſtill continued the maine Battell, vntill three a clocke in the afternoone; about which time, <hi>Mansfields</hi> horſemen played the Deuill amongſt the Bores, as themſelues repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after the Battell. Theſe aforeſaid horſemen put the Bores to rout, and beat them backe amaine, and recouered the Ordenance from them; and indeed, was the chiefeſt cauſe that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> remained Maſter of the Field, as you ſhall preſently vnderſtand. Theſe horſemen hauing obtained the Ordenance from the Bores, put them into ſuch a feare, that they became wholly diſordered: which aduantage the <hi>Mansfeldaans</hi> eſpying, fell vpon them, and flew a great number of them, moſt of them being Bores, and continually put forwards by the old Souldiers. By which meanes, Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> obtaining the beſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained <hi>Don Cordua</hi> to ſound a retreat. Nay further, it is certified, that if ſome of Count <hi>Mansfields</hi> horſemen had taken an opportunitie, which fortunately was proffered them, they had vtterly ouerthrowne and diſcomfited <hi>Don Cordua's</hi> Forces; which, when he muſtered about <hi>Lier,</hi> conſiſted of two thouſand horſe and eight thouſand foot, the moſt whereof, were old and well experienced Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. In this fight it is moſt credibly reported, that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> hath ſlain very neere a thouſand of the enemies,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176342:11"/>amongſt whom, was ſlaine a great Commander, <hi>Don Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſco Geuana.</hi> He hath likewiſe taken moſt of his Ordnance, all his Munition and Treaſure, beſides two Waggons of Plate, all which are ſafely arriued in <hi>Breda.</hi> Here all the Treaſure was diuided amongſt <hi>Mansfields</hi> and <hi>Brunſwicks</hi> ſouldiers. Likewiſe Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> hath burned &amp; ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led moſt part of the Countrey in his paſſage through it, as alſo the corne on the field. Here it is certified, that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> loſt not in this Battell aboue 1000. men, but hee loſt aboue 2000. but not all cut off by the Sword, as you ſhall heare. The Battell being ended, Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> with his Forces departed towards <hi>Breda:</hi> but before his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuall there, hee loſt 1200. the occaſion of whoſe deaths, were the inhabitants dwelling in thoſe parts; who vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> was maſter of the field, and that he afterwards intended to march with his Forces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Magiſtrats or Gouernor of euery Towne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts; gaue priuat command, that Springs or Ditches of Water which lay in their paſſage towards <hi>Breda,</hi> ſhould be infected with ſtrong poyſon, and by this denilliſh inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they loſt within the compaſſe of twelue dayes aboue 1200, men, onely with drinking their poyſoned waters, ſo that euery day they loſt 100.: it ſeems by this that <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> loſt more me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by 200, that were poyſon'd, then he had cut off by the ſword in the battel. Before they were at <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ſent to refreſh his army 30000. loaues, beſides other prouiſion, which was welcome to the ſouldiers: after they were arriued, the towne welcomed them royally, ſhooting off all their Ordnance, making Bonefires, ringing of Bels, warlicke Inſtruments, &amp; good prouiſion for the common ſouldiers, withal the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they were able to make them. After they were well refreſhed, Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> trained them in good diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176342:11"/>of war almoſt euery day: he hath brought with him 6000. of the beſt horſe in Chriſtendome, and 4000. foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; beſides a great number wearied and ſicke men, which come dayly to him in great numbers. I beleeue you had a falſe report was ſpred all ouer theſe countries, that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> had ſent 3000. men to meete with <hi>Don Cordua,</hi> which loſing their way, were cut off by the Biſhop of <hi>Luckes</hi> forces; but for certaine, there is no ſuch matter, for Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> neuer ſent out a man to meete with <hi>Don Cordua,</hi> before <hi>Don Cordua</hi> himſelfe met with him. It is certainly reported that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> had a skirmiſh with <hi>Don Cordua</hi> before his entrance into <hi>Henego,</hi> in which <hi>Don Cerdua</hi> had the worſt; but afterwards hauing that great ſupply of the Bores of that countrey, did make a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great oppoſition againſt Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> in which was ſlaine aboue 1000. men on both ſides. At <hi>Mansfields</hi> firſt comming into the Prouince of <hi>Henego,</hi> the Bores of the countrey vnderſtanding of his comming, had carryed away all their prouiſion, that for the ſpace of foure or ſiue dayes Count <hi>Mansfields</hi> forces found no more to feede vpon then what the trees did affoord them, which bred a great weakneſſe in his whole army: but ſhortly after they found very good paſture in that fruitfull Dukedome of <hi>Brabant;</hi> nay I do abſolutely thinke it to be the fruitfulleſt and richeſt in all the ſeuenteene. It is further certified, that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> hath gathered in a readineſſe 4000. the braueſt horſe thoſe Prouinces can yeeld, to ioyne with <hi>Mansfields</hi> horſe. Moreouer there are to be brought to the Graue of <hi>Lipſtat</hi> 2000. more, al which makes 12000. horſe, which hath ſeldome been ſeene in the States iuriſdictions. Further it is thought his Excellency hath ready in ſeuerall places, betwixt 30. &amp; 40000. foote: here is now great like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of bloody wars in this country, for that <hi>Don Cordus</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:176342:12"/>likewiſe receiueth greater helpes from the Palatinate, and that the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> is comming downe to ayde <hi>Don Cordua</hi> with great forces. Here it is at this preſent repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that <hi>Gonzales de Corduas</hi> forces are arriued at <hi>Antwerp</hi> and there remaineth, for that it is greatly feared amongſt them, that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> will beſiege the ſame, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo many forces in a readineſſe. Here it is thought the chiefe rendez-vous of the States warre will bee in and about <hi>Breda,</hi> both to draw the enemies forces from great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offending others, and defence of their owne, knowing that a warre maintained in the enemies countrey, is very preualent to weary, or ouercome. And it is thought, though that <hi>Mansfield</hi> wil plant his army betwixt <hi>Antwerp</hi> and <hi>Bergen vp Zome,</hi> to imbarre all prouiſions from <hi>Spino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> army, Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> hath left the one halfe of his foote with the Duke <hi>de Boulloign,</hi> as alſo his munition: the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> is certainly more grieued for the loſſe of his Standerd, then for the loſſe of his arme. Some ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers comming hither, bring newes that certain letters are written by the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Brabant</hi> to <hi>Spinola,</hi> wherein are diſcloſed diuers ſecrets of ſtrange plots againſt the States and other Princes, to the States great aduantage. This day the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> being in the great Hall of the town, the Duke ſhewed himſelfe with a merry countenance, and ſeemes prettily amended, and paſt danger at the cutting off his arme, beſeeching God that he might recouer of his wound, to be reuenged of his enemies.</p>
               <p>Count <hi>Mansfields</hi> forces that remained here, haue three ſeuerall times taken and ſpoyled great ſtore of waggons with victuals that was carrying to <hi>Spinolas</hi> campe before <hi>Bergen;</hi> and alſo hath ſlaine their conuoyes, ſo that no vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals can be brought to releeue the ſouldiers which are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176342:12"/>in great want: what hereafter will follow, you ſhall weeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Zeland the <hi>4.</hi> of September.</head>
               <p>It is certainly reported that ſome foure dayes paſt <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nola</hi> made a violent Aſſault vpon <hi>Bergen vp Zome,</hi> but he was repulſed with the loſſe of 600. men,</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Spinolas</hi> ſouldiers, by reaſon of the ſmall and bad pay, ſcarcity of victuals, and that all things in their campe are very deere, which eauſeth them dayly to runne away, as many as can finde any opportunity, ariuing continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at <hi>Dort, Middleberg,</hi> and in other places elſe, where they thinke themſelues to be freeſt.</p>
               <p>It is alſo certainly affirmed by diuers letters from <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> that all the townes haue conſented to make vp 16000. of the Burgers to goe and lie in the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier townes: whereby if occaſion ſerue, the old and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſoldiers may ioyn the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is further reported, that <hi>Spinola</hi> hauing intelligence that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> was ouerthrowne, did for ioy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of giue order that there ſhould be Boneſires made in his Campe, and all his Ordnance diſcharged againſt the towne, which did put the towne into great amazement: but not long after the towne had order from his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency for to make Bonefires, and to ſhew ſome ioy for the comming of <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſafely to <hi>Bredaw,</hi> which thoſe in <hi>Spinolas</hi> leaguer perceiuing fire, were alſo put into great amazement, and ſome of the boldeſt ſpirits of them did attempt to draw neere to the towne, to view the occaſion of the fire in the town: which the towne perceiuing, made way for the enemy to come to their owne deſtruction, for they were all ſlaine, but the number vncertaine. It is alſo reported, that the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> is comming downe to ayd <hi>Don Cordua,</hi> but with what number we know not.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
